MASSIMINO Pascal

Compression - Image & Media processing - Large-Scale Engineering

C++, assembly (NEON, x86), GLSL, and anything around to make these work and shipped at scale.

Deep hands-on 'get things done' engineering, along with a researcher mindset. Hardware and software.

pascal.massimino@gmail.com cell: +33 6 51 92 05 90 - Paris Area - https://skal65535.github.io

EXPERIENCE

Google — Principal Engineer

2006 - PRESENT:

- Streetview: imagery, backend, serving, jpeg compression (used everywhere at Google)
- YouTube: back-end, video compression, thumbnails, processing pipeline, Video for VR
- WebP: initiator of the format, wrote most of the initial code, worked with the ecosystem on adoption and user support.
 - Public talks to influencers: 2020 WebP Rewind, 2021 WebP Recap
 - WebP2: Next-gen format my team and I experimented with.
 - Researched compressing images in ~200 bytes
- AOMedia: developing AV1/AVIF video codec with industry partners.
 - Public advocate and speakers: #1 in french, #2, #3, slides, ...
- Manager of small dedicated team
- 21 US patents

XviD Solutions GmbH — Co-Founder

2000 - 2007, Video Codec Consulting & Development

Co-Founded Xvid Solutions to leverage the open-source development of the XviD code (in Ffmpeg notably).

Wrote MPEG2, H263, H264 codecs for various DSP platforms in all sorts of low-level languages. Shipped in volume to numerous set-top boxes and home devices.

Ilog, Paris — Senior Engineer

2000–2005, Operation Research and Constraint Propagation technology. Worked on the flagship Scheduler product until the acquisition by IBM.

EDUCATION and RESEARCH

PhD, 1999 — Theoretical Physics

- Elastic Ising Models : Modèle d'Ising compressible (in french)
- Effect of magnetoelastic interactions on the phase transition of two-dimensional Ising spin system

Alma mater: Ecole Normale Superieure de Paris (1991 - Promo B91)

SIDE INTERESTS

- FinTech: business angel and investor, notably for Kard
- Entrepreneur / consulting: metaskal.com
- Marathon & Trail runner Rock Climbing Muay Thai Music & Rock band

